Animation Number 1
No, I've been thinking for a while now
（戦場ヶ原(せんじょうがはら)）
いえ 昔から考えてはいたのよ
about how you and Araragi-kun differ, Hanekawa-san.
阿良々木(あららぎ)くんと羽川(はねかわ)さんの違いって
どこにあるのかって
Both of you sacrifice yourselves to help others with such zeal.
同じように２人とも
我が身を犠牲にして
他人のために 躍起になるけれど
But in my eyes, you have almost nothing in common.
どうも 私から見れば
両者は 全く別物のように思える
You seem like totally different beings.
似てさえいないように思える
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
In simpler terms, it feels like Araragi-kun is a fake, and you're the real thing, Hanekawa-san.
分かりやすく言えば
阿良々木くんが偽物で
羽川さんが本物に見える
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
You're doing the same thing, but why do I feel this way?
（戦場ヶ原）
やってることは同じなのに
なんでなのかなって
I think I understand from this meal you made.
でも この手料理を食べて
分かった気がするわ
You understand now?
（羽川）
“分かった気がする”って…
It feels like a cooking manga where I can figure out people's qualities by eating their cooking.
手料理を食べて
相手の人となりが分かるなんて
某料理漫画みたいだけれどね
Purple Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Like Oishinbo.
「美味(おい)しんぼ」みたいだけれどね
Why'd you mention the title anyway?
（羽川）
なぜ 一度 伏せたタイトルを
改めて…
There's a difference in awareness of danger between you and Araragi-kun.
（戦場ヶ原）
危うさに対する認識が違うのよ
阿良々木くんと あなたでは
For instance, if a cat were killed on the street by a car
例えば 道路で車にひかれて
死んでいる猫がいるとして
giving it a proper burial is probably the correct course of action.
その猫を埋葬してあげるという
行為は きっと正しい
I'm sure that's what you would do.
羽川さんは そうするんだと思うし
Araragi-kun probably would as well, though he'd be grumbling the whole time.
阿良々木くんも
なんだかんだ言いながら
そうするかもしれない
I'm sure the difference is the
"grumbling the whole time" part.
違うのは
この“なんだかんだ言う”
という部分なのよね きっと
Why do so many people ignore that cat and pass by as if nothing had happened?
なぜ 多くの人が猫を無視し
まるで 何も見なかったかのように
通り過ぎるのかと言えば
Because it's "dangerous" to give it a burial.
その猫を埋葬することが
危ういからよ
Because there's a very high risk when society knows
自分が いい人 善人であることを
周囲に知られることは
that you're a "good, virtuous person."
人間社会では 非常に高いリスク
There's a very high chance someone will exploit you.
つけ込まれる可能性が 非常に高い
Open
Ignite
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Araragi-kun probably knows pretending to be a bad person is safer.
悪ぶることが安全だということを
阿良々木くんは 多分 分かっている
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
You, on the other hand, don't understand that at all.
対して 羽川さんは
その辺が全く理解できていない
No, that's not it. I'm sure you also realize such a risk exists,
いえ 違うわ
きっと あなたにだって
そのリスクの存在は
分かっているはず
but you don't think it's that big a deal.
だけど そのリスクを
全然 大したことだと思っていない
That's probably it. You don't regret anything.
そこなのよ 多分
あなたは 何も後悔していない
You don't feel anything about the ill will people have.
悪意やダメさを
まるで ものともしていない
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Or rather...
というより
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
You accept them all as they are. You're probably just too white.
受け入れてしまっている
多分 あなたは白すぎる
You're too pure a white.
白無垢(むく)すぎる
You're not supposed to accept everything.
全てを受け入れちゃ ダメなのよ
You have no sense of alarm against stupid or bad things.
あなたは バカさやダメさに対して
何の警戒心も持っていない
Even though you know you'll be
exploited, you do good deeds anyway.
人から つけ込まれることが
分かっていても
何とも思わず 善行に走り
Even though you know you'll distance
yourself from others, you try to stay logical.
集団の中で浮いてしまうことが
分かっていても
倫理的であろうとする
Yummy Milk
To conclude, you're not a good person nor a saint nor a madonna.
結論として あなたは
いい人なんじゃなくって
聖人でも 聖母でもなくって
You're just thick-headed when it comes to shadows.
闇に鈍いだけだわ
それじゃ—
In that case...
You will be a failure in the wild.
野性として落第よ
Naoetsu High School - Classroom
Animation Number 51
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Failure...?
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（羽川）
落第…
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Failure, failure, failure...
落第 落第 落第…
つまり
In other words, I'm white. I'm too white. I'm pure white.
白くて
白すぎて
白無垢で
The whitest of whites...
白々しい
Animation Number 62
But then as I was sitting in class,
my attention was drawn to the scribbles
in Senjougahara's textbook.
Animation Number 62
I must admit that I felt like words were just popping up meaninglessly in my head.
Tsubasa Tiger          Part Three
Font used in the video: HGP Mincho B
Animation Number 65
Naoetsu High School
Kanbaru Suruga
Animation Number 77
Suruga
Animation Number 78
（神原(かんばる)の鼻歌）
Suruga
She noticed me.
Animation Number 78
Considering that we were in the corridor,
she was really loud.
Animation Number 81
If it isn't Hanekawa-senpai!
羽川先輩ではないか！
An accelerator
Animation Number 83
It's been a while. Glad to see you're well!
久しぶりだな
お元気そうで何よりだ
Yeah...
I was just on my way to see Senjougahara-senpai.
（神原）
実は今 戦場ヶ原先輩に
会いに行く道中だったのだけれど
Is she in the classroom?
教室におられるかな？
Um...
え〜っと
Senjougahara-san is absent from school today. She caught influenza.
戦場ヶ原さんは 今日 お休みだよ
I became her accomplice in her lie.
Animation Number 92
インフルエンザに
かかって
Hmm, I see. She isn't here? What should I do?
（神原）ん〜 そうか
戦場ヶ原先輩は いないのか
どうしよう
Did you have something for Senjougahara-san?
（羽川）
戦場ヶ原さんに
何か用事でもあったの？
If you want to tell me, I can at least listen.
私でよかったら 話 聞くよ？
I guess you'll have to do!
じゃあ 羽川先輩でいいか
（羽川）アハ…
She's polite,
but inconsiderate
Animation Number 97
Actually, I just got a text from Araragi-senpai.
Tonight at nine,
second floor, come to
the classroom alone.
There's something
I have to ask you.
Tonight at nine,
second floor, come to
the classroom alone.
There's something
I have to ask you.
実は ついさっき
阿良々木先輩から
メールが届いたのだ
Tonight
at nine,
second
floor,
come
to the
classroom
alone.
There's
something
I have to
ask you.
Tonight
at nine,
second
floor,
come
to the
classroom
alone.
There's
something
I have to
ask you.
What do you think this means?
これ どういう意味だと思う？
There's no other meaning.
（羽川）どういう意味も何も…
He has something to tell you,
阿良々木くんが
神原さんに質問があるから
so he wants you to go to the second-floor classroom at nine o'clock tonight, right?
今晩の９時に １人で２階の教室に
来てくれって意味でしょう？
So that is it. He's so troublesome sometimes.
（神原）やはり そうか
阿良々木先輩にも
困ったものだな
This meeting place of a "second-floor classroom" is too vague.
２階の教室とは
待ち合わせ場所が
漠然としすぎている
How many buildings does he think Naoetsu High has?
直江津(なおえつ)高校に一体 いくつ
校舎があると思っているのだろう
No, not our school. I think he means the cram-school ruins.
（羽川）
いや これ 学校じゃなくって
例の学習塾跡って意味でしょう？
Oh, really?
あっ そうなのか？
But he could've called me then.
でも それなら
電話してくれればいいのに
Actually, I tried calling several times but couldn't get through.
実は さっき
電話をひっきりなしに
かけてみたのだけど つながらない
Animation Number 110
So this means he's asking me out on a date?
つまり これは
デートの誘いということだな
He must not be answering because he's preparing some surprise.
電話に出ないのは
何らかのサプライズを
用意してくれているからに違いない
Don't you think it's more serious based on his wording?
いや 文面的に もっと
シリアスなものだとは思わないの？
I see. I see. I'm convinced.
（神原）
そうか そうか
ならば 得心いった
I wanted to read a book tonight, but I've got no choice if he's asking me out.
今晩は 読みたい本が
あったけれど
阿良々木先輩に
呼び出されたのならば 是非もない
I'll oblige his request of my presence at any cost.
私は 万難を排して
阿良々木先輩の呼び出しに応じよう
At any cost?
万難を排して…
Well, Hanekawa-senpai, thanks for telling me all this.
（神原）
では 羽川先輩
いろいろ教えてくれてありがとう
Not at all. You're welcome.
（羽川）
いえいえ どういたしまして
I heard your house caught fire, so I thought you'd be down
家が火事になったと聞いて
落ち込んでいるかと思ったが
but I'm relieved to see nothing of the sort.
別段そんなこともないようで
安心したぞ
I can't believe she acts like this even though she knows.
Animation Number 121
As expected of Hanekawa-senpai.
さすが 羽川先輩だ
No.
Animation Number 123
Did she really know?
（羽川）
本当に知っていたのか？
Why did she say I don't seem to be feeling down?
Animation Number 124
Then best of luck.
（神原）では ご武運を！
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
It's unreasonable.
Animation Number 133
（羽川）
筋違いだ
There must be some need for Araragi-kun to specifically text Kanbaru-san.
阿良々木くんは 必然性があって
神原さんにメールを打ったに
違いないのだから
So it's unreasonable for me to be mulling over him asking Kanbaru-san for help instead.
私じゃなくて神原さんに
助力を求めたことについて
物思うのは
That's why I think I'm being unreasonable.
Animation Number 137
筋違いだ
Animation Number 139
1 0 2
Oh, welcome back.
Senjougahara
Animation Number 143
（戦場ヶ原）
あら おかえりなさい
Hanekawa-san, you're quite late.
羽川さん 遅かったわね
Yeah. I stopped by the supermarket to restock the food I used for breakfast... Oh?
（羽川）
うん 朝 使わせてもらった
食材の補充に
スーパーに寄ってたから… って
Nice to meet you. I'm Hitagi's father.
（戦場ヶ原の父）
はじめまして　ひたぎの父です
（羽川）
あ… えっと 羽川翼(つばさ)です
Um, I'm Hanekawa Tsubasa. Excuse me for having slept over last night.
すみません
昨晩は泊めていただきました
He texted Kanbaru? How unpleasant.
（戦場ヶ原）神原にメール？
なんと不愉快な
To think Araragi-kun would seek that woman's help over mine.
私を差し置いて 阿良々木くんに
助けを求められるなど あの女
What should I do? First, disembowel.
どうしてやろうかしら
まずは 内臓を…
Your persona's turning back from its new leaf.
戦場ヶ原さん
キャラが更生前に戻ってる
Whoops.
おっと
I'm sure there's a reason.
（羽川）
多分 理由があるんだと思うよ
その点については
Concerning that, the fact he has
something to ask must be part of it.
聞きたいことがあるっていうのも
そうだろうし
After all, unlike us, Kanbaru-san's
aberration remains in her left arm, right?
だって 私や戦場ヶ原さんと違って
神原さんは 左腕に怪異を
残しているじゃない？
It does.
（戦場ヶ原）残しているわね
In other words, he doesn't want
Kanbaru per se, but rather just her left arm?
つまり 神原というより
神原の左腕が
必要ということなのかしら
Well, it's just a guess.
（羽川）まあ 推測だけれど…
So what will you do?
（戦場ヶ原）
で どうするの？　羽川さんは
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Do what?
（羽川）どうするって？
Will you go? Or will you not?
その待ち合わせ場所に
行くの？　行かないの？
No matter what condition he's in, you could see Araragi-kun if you go.
彼の状況は どうあれ
そこに行けば 阿良々木くんには
会えるわけでしょ？
I thought about it, but I'm not planning to. I have a feeling I'd get in the way if I did.
考えたけど 行かないつもり
行ったら
邪魔しちゃいそうな気もするし
I see. Then I won't go either.
そう　じゃあ 私も行かない
Really?
そう？
I'll just go with "no news is good news."
（戦場ヶ原）
便りがないのは元気な証拠だと
思っておくことにするわ
Unlike the time with Kanbaru's monkey,
それこそ 神原の猿のときと違って
it doesn't seem like he's really trying to hide something.
何か隠し事をしようとしている
というわけでも なさそうだし
You won't go?
（羽川）行かないの？
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（戦場ヶ原）行かないわ
I won't.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Like you, I feel I'd only get in the way.
羽川さんと同じよ
行っても
邪魔しかできそうにないから
Besides, I have a feeling there's
something else that I can be doing.
それに 私にできることは
ほかにありそう
という気もするのよね
But it seems Araragi-kun and Kanbaru aren't the only ones who still have aberrations in them.
しかし 体に怪異を残しているのは
どうやら
Cold
阿良々木くんと神原だけじゃ
なかったみたいだけれど
Who else?
え？　ほかに誰かいるの？
The only aberrations left around us are Araragi-kun's demon and Kanbaru-san's monkey, right?
私たちの周りで
残っている怪異って
阿良々木くんの鬼と
神原さんの猿だけでしょ？
That's right, meow.
そのとおりにゃん
（ノック）
（戦場ヶ原）おっと 来たようね
Whoa. They're here.
I braced myself for a moment, wondering who it was.
（羽川）
一体 誰だろうと
私は やや身構えたけれど
But when Senjougahara-san opened the door and I saw those girls, I understood everything.
戦場ヶ原さんがドアを開けて
その向こうにいた
女の子の姿を見て
私は 全てを理解する
Trump      card
Animation Number 185
It was Araragi-kun's younger sisters.
そこにいたのは
阿良々木くんの妹
Araragi Karen-chan and Araragi Tsukihi-chan, The Fire Sisters.
阿良々木火憐(かれん)ちゃんと
阿良々木月火(つきひ)ちゃんの
ファイヤーシスターズだったのだ
Animation Number 187
After school - the Araragi residence
Animation Number 188
Apparently, they had a conversation like this.
こんな会話が
あったらしい
Oh, what's this? If it isn't Karen-san. What a coincidence to see you here.
あらあら これは これは
火憐さんじゃない
こんな所で会うなんて 偶然ね
And if it isn't Senjougahara-san!
（火憐）
おお　そういう あんたは
戦場ヶ原さんじゃねえか
This really is a coincidence, running into you in front of my house.
本当に偶然だな
こうして
私の家の前で会うだなんて
But Senjougahara-san, what about school?
あれ？
でも 戦場ヶ原さん 学校は？
School? What's that?
（戦場ヶ原）学校？　何それ？
If you don't know, that's fine...
（火憐）
いや 知らないんなら いいんだけど
I kid. I know. It's a Gahara-joke. That reminds me.
（戦場ヶ原）
ウソウソ　知ってるわよ
ガハラジョークよ
ああ そういえば
I just remembered this out of the blue.
今 唐突に つまり不意に
思い出したのだけれど 知ってる？
Did you know that Hanekawa-san's house burned down?
羽川さんの家が 火事になったこと
Bolt from the blue
Animation Number 195
Sorry, that was a silly question.
（戦場ヶ原）
あっ ごめん ごめん
愚問だったわね
There's no way you, the mobile half of the heroes of justice, the Fire Sisters,
正義の味方
ファイヤーシスターズの実戦担当
この町の平和を一身に担う
阿良々木火憐さんともあろう人が
who upholds the peace of this town,
wouldn't know of such a huge incident.
そんな大事件を
知らないはずがないわよね
Oh, yeah, yeah, of course I knew.
ん？　ああ！　うんうん もちろん
知ってる 知ってる
That must have been rough. I was just thinking of paying Tsubasa-san a consolation visit.
大変だったよな
なんなら今から 翼さんを訪ねて
お見舞いを お見舞いしようかと
思ってたところだったぜ
Hanekawa-san wasn't injured. But without a home, she has no place to sleep tonight.
（戦場ヶ原）
羽川さんに
ケガは なかったんだけれどね
でも 焼け出されちゃって
彼女 今晩 寝る場所もないのよ
Really?
（火憐）えっ そうなの？
You didn't know?
（戦場ヶ原）知らなかった？
No, I knew! I was just about to bring up that subject.
いや 知ってた 知ってた
今 私のほうから その話題を
振ろうと思ってたところだぜ
Why do you say everything before me?
なんで 先に言っちゃうのかな？
戦場ヶ原さんは
I'm sorry.
（戦場ヶ原）ごめんなさいね
But it really is strange that there's no bed in this world a good girl like her can get a good night's sleep on.
でも 本当 不思議よね
羽川さんみたいな いい子が
ぐっすり眠れるベッドが
この世に ないだなんて
It feels like the epitome of absurdity.
理不尽も これ極まれり
といった感じだわ
It's like I'd want to ask what justice is doing right now if it existed in this world.
いや もう
この世に正義があるのなら
一体 何をしているのか
という感じだわ
Animation Number 203
Well, justice is empty and ineffectual,
まあ お題目だけの
正義が何もしてくれないから
so I'm actually taking off from school today to find Hanekawa-san a roof to sleep under.
実は 私は 今日は学校を休んで
羽川さんの寝床を
探しているというわけなのよ
Araragi
Whoa, sorry. Even if I'm telling you this, it's not like you can help.
おっと ごめん ごめん
こんなこと 火憐さんに話しても
しかたのないことだったわね
After all, though you're Araragi Koyomi's younger sister, you're merely a junior-high student.
だって 火憐さんは
あの阿良々木暦(こよみ)の
妹だっていうだけで
所詮は ただの中学生なんだから
The expectations would be too heavy if I treated you like Araragi-kun.
阿良々木くんと同じように扱っちゃ
期待が重すぎるわよね
You can't do anything without your dear older
brother, so I only troubled you by mentioning this.
大好きなお兄ちゃんがいなきゃ
何もできない火憐さんに
こんなことを話しても
迷惑だったわね
I'm truly sorry. I guess I'll be on my way now.
本当にごめんなさい
じゃあ そろそろ私 行くわね
Purple Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Just like there's no place for Hanekawa-san to sleep, I know there's no justice in this world.
羽川さんの寝床同様
この世に正義がないということも
分かったことだし
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Yellow Scene
Blue Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Red Scene
Hold on a second!
Nishizono
Life
Clinic
Nishizono
Life
Clinic
（火憐）ちょっと待った〜！
The fox
Animation Number 217
jumped in the well
on its own.
Animation Number 217
What? Is something wrong?
えっ 何？　どうかしたの？
There is a place for Tsubasa-san to sleep! And there is justice!
翼さんの寝床はある
そして 正義もある！
Araragi residence     Living room
/
Animation Number 220
And so I'm now at the Araragi residence.
（羽川）
そんなわけで
私は 阿良々木家に来ていた
Relax. Think of this as your own home, Tsubasa-san.
（火憐）
まあまあ 自分の家だと思って
くつろいでよ 翼さん
That's right! Think of this as your home! It's all yours, Hanekawa-san.
（月火）
そうだよ　自分の家だと思ってよ
思いまくっちゃってよ
（月火）羽川さん
You're pretty risqué anyway, Tsubasa-san.
（火憐）
大体 水っぽいんだよな〜 翼さんは
I think she meant reserved,
not risqué
Animation Number 228
If you didn't have a place to sleep,
you could've come to me first and foremost.
寝る場所がねえなら
まず いの一番に
私を頼ってくれれば よかったんだ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I've been waiting for you to approach me about this.
いや もう 私は翼さんが
自分から言ってくれるのを待ってた
But I thought it was hard for you to bring it up, so I offered.
まあ 言いにくいのかなって思って
こうして 自分から
提案したわけだけれど
Yeah.
そうだね
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
You were the one who made the offer, Karen-chan.
火憐ちゃんは
自分から提案したんだよね
In any case, if you don't have a place to stay, you can stay here as long as you want.
とにかく 羽川さん
泊まる場所がないっていうなら
うちに いくらでも
泊まっていってよ
Fortunately for you, our brother isn't here right now. So you can use his room.
都合のいいことに
お兄ちゃんが 今 お留守だからさ
お兄ちゃんの部屋を使って
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
But you're right. I'll accept the favor and spend some time here.
（羽川）でも そうだね
じゃあ お言葉に甘えて
お世話になるね
I'll stay until Araragi-kun comes home, so
阿良々木くんが
帰ってくるまでの間ってことで
I'm in your care.
よろしくお願いします
As are we.
よろしく
Let's get along well.
よろしくお願いします
That's right. Since I'll be a guest for many days, I need to say hello to your parents.
そうだ！
何日もお世話になる以上
さすがに ご両親にご挨拶を
しないわけには いかないよね
I think it'll be fine.
それは 大丈夫だと思うよ
I mean, we're related by blood, so our personalities are similar.
私たちと それに お兄ちゃんの
パパとママなんだから
性格も それなりだよ
え… でもさ
But still...
They both have a passion for justice, so they'd never tell someone in need to get out.
（月火）
２人とも
熱血な正義感の持ち主だから
困っている人に
出ていけなんて言わないよ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Say, Karen-chan and Tsukihi-chan,
ねえ 火憐ちゃん 月火ちゃん
I'd like to know for reference, but you said before that your parents both work, right?
参考までに聞きたいんだけど
前に お父さんとお母さん
共働きだって言ってたよね
I think they'll come home around six today.
（月火）
今日は ６時くらいに
帰ってくると思う
Animation Number 248
What kind of work do they do?
お仕事は 何をされているのかな？
Together they said...
Animation Number 249
They're police officers!
（２人）警察官！
Animation Number 250
There was trouble of course.
（羽川）
もちろん ひともんちゃく あった
But the Araragi pair simply said, "If that's the case, there's nothing we can do."
けれど 阿良々木夫妻は
それでも 思ったよりも あっさり
“そういう事情なら
しかたがない”と
It wasn't with a very positive attitude, but in the end, they gave permission for me to stay over.
決して 積極的にでは
なかったけれど
最終的には 私の宿泊に
お許しを出してくれた
As expected, they gave the feeling that they were Araragi-kun's parents.
そこは やはり
確かに阿良々木くんの両親
という感じだった
But still, was this the "good idea" Senjougahara-san mentioned?
（羽川）
それにしても
これが 戦場ヶ原さんが言っていた
いいアイデアか
Senjougahara planted this idea in Karen's head.
Animation Number 258
That was her "trump card."
やだ やだ やだ　もう
I'm gonna get bubbles in my eyes!
目に入っちゃうよ
I felt like I played upon the Fire Sisters' sense of justice
（羽川）
なんというか
ファイヤーシスターズの正義感に
つけ込んだみたいで
and couldn't help but feel a touch of guilt.
若干以上の後ろめたさを
感じざるをえないけれど
Lilac Scene
Animation Number 'none'
But Senjougahara-san had put the
villain's role on her shoulders for me.
悪役みたいなところを
戦場ヶ原さんは 全部
自分で背負ってくれたのだ
それに…
And...
I've been waiting for you to approach me about this.
いや もう 私は翼さんが
自分から言ってくれるのを待ってた
It was the same
Animation Number 273
I never seek out help for myself.
（羽川）
私は 自分から助けを
求めるようなことがなく
when Senjougahara let me
Animation Number 273
stay at her place.
This is probably completely different reasoning from Oshino-san's "people just help themselves."
これは きっと
忍野(おしの)さんが言うところの
“人は勝手に
１人で助かるだけ”とは
全然 違う理屈なんだろうな
That's right, I'm probably in desperation time.
そう　多分 私は…
I remember the words Senjougahara said to me this morning.
Animation Number 278
自暴自棄なのだ
I don't think I can survive by myself.
１人で助かろうとも思っていない
I've come to accept the bland. I'm dull against the shadows.
私は 味気のなさを受け入れていて
And in the wild, I'm a failure.
闇に鈍く
野性として
落第
You don't put on airs.
（火憐）
翼さんって気取らないよな
Or more like when I'm talking to a smart guy at school, I often think, "Are you really smart?"
なんつうか
学校で頭のいいヤツと話してると
“お前 本当に頭いいのかよ”って
思うことが 多々あるんだよな
Like when they use hard words or
reference stuff I don't want to know.
妙に難しい言葉を並べたり
知りたくもねえ引用をしたりよ
Still, you're smart, but you always talk to us at our level.
でも 翼さんって 頭いいのに
Yellow Scene
Animation Number 'none'
私とかと同じ視点で
話してくれるじゃん？
Stuff like that makes me happy!
そういうのって うれしいんだよな
Blue Scene
Animation Number 'none'
You're right. But they say that's how things really are, Karen-chan.
そうだね
でも 実際 そういうものらしいよ
火憐ちゃん
White Scene
Animation Number 'none'
People who are really smart, or rather, whether it be sports or whatever,
本当に頭がいい人
ていうか スポーツでも何でも
いわゆる 一流の人って
"first-class" people are surprisingly ordinary when you talk to them. They have no auras.
話してみたら
意外と普通の人だったりして
オーラとかも
全然なかったりするんだよ
But maybe because they're real, they don't have to embellish themselves.
でも それって つまり
本物だからこそ
飾らないってことなのかな？
Araragi's room
Animation Number 301
Discomfort
Animation Number 302
Huh? Aren't these men's pajamas?
（羽川）
あれ？　このパジャマ
男物じゃない？
Oh, those are our brother's.
ん？　ああ それ 兄ちゃんの
What's with this
Animation Number 305
（羽川）
ぐは！
"wow, I did it" feeling?
Animation Number 305
Well, good night, Tsubasa-san. Use anything you want in here.
じゃあ おやすみなさい 翼さん
この部屋のものは
好きに使っていいから
Good night, Hanekawa-san. I'll see you tomorrow.
おやすみなさい 羽川さん
また明日ね
In any case...
（羽川）
それにしたって
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
The thought that I was then wearing Araragi-kun's pajamas,
今 阿良々木くんのパジャマを着て
阿良々木くんのベッドに潜って
crawling in his bed, and resting my head on his pillow
阿良々木くんの枕に
頭を添えているのだと思うと
was keeping me from falling asleep. And I think I actually didn't fall asleep until around midnight.
全然 寝つけず
実際に眠りについたのは
Reference
てっぺんを回ったころだったと
思うけれど
But I can't blame Araragi-kun. I'm naughty for having thoughts like that.
阿良々木くんのことを
責められない
そんなことを考えてしまう私は
はしたない
Animation Number 315
（ブラック羽川）う… さて
Nyow then, what should I do about this?
しかし どうしたもんかにゃ
Since I've come out like this again, it's obvious my myaster is carrying around some sort of stress.
いつまでたっても
こうして俺が出てきている以上
ご主人が また 何(にゃん)らかのストレスを
抱えていることは
確かにゃんだが
Hanekawa
I thought it was the house burning down, but since I'm here that's inyarguably not the case.
自宅の火事が原因だと
決めつけていたけど
どうも 火事の件だけじゃ
にゃさそうだよにゃ
Lilac Scene
Animation Number 'none'
It's truly flexible for me that I can show up only when my myaster is asleep.
まっ ご主人が寝ている間だけ
限定で登場できるというのは
実にフレキシブルにゃん
Lilac Scene
Animation Number 'none'
The previous two times, they had quite a bit of trouble suppurressing me.
前の２回は
俺を引っ込めるためだけに
あいつら 随分 苦労してたからにゃ
Like when they borrowed the power of that short vampire.
ニャッハハ
あの ちびっこい吸血鬼の力を
借りたりにゃ
Yellow Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Who's a short vampire?
Yellow Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（忍(しのぶ)）
誰が ちびっこい
吸血鬼じゃ？
Yellow Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Meow?
It's been a while, cat. Though I don't know why you're in my master's room.
久しいのう 猫
どうして うぬが 我が主(あるじ)様の
部屋におるのかは知らんが
I guess it's bad taste to ask why an aberration has appeared, I'm not that Hawaiian-shirt guy.
まっ 怪異に出現の理由など
求めるほうが 不粋というものか
あのアロハでもあるまいし
Wait, weren't you trapped inside that humyan boy's shadow?
ちゅうか あれ？
そもそも お前 確か
あの人間野郎の影に
閉じ込められてたんじゃ
にゃかったのかにゃ？
Well, I was, but there were a few irregularities.
（忍）まあ そうなのじゃがな
ちょっとイレギュラーな事態が
起こっての
Right now, the pairing between me and my master, Oshino Shinobu and Araragi Koyomi, has been severed.
現在 わしと我が主様…
つまり 忍野忍と阿良々木暦との
ペアリングは切られておる
ん？　切られて…？
Severed?
I thought perhaps my master would be home, but I guess that was the slightest of hopes.
（忍）ひょっとしたら 我が主様は
自宅に戻っておるかとも
思ったのじゃが
淡い期待じゃったようじゃのう
And I find you here instead. It feels like I avenged someone who died in Edo way over in Nagasaki.
どころか
うぬがおったというのじゃから
こりゃあ 江戸の敵(かたき)を
長崎で討ったような気分じゃわい
Your myaster should've been at the cram-school ruins back around nine o'clock.
お前の主様にゃら
今晩の９時の段階で
例の学習塾跡にいたはずにゃ
He was meeting that monkey girl.
例の猿の女(おんにゃ)と待ち合わせでにゃ
Meeting her? But why the monkey now of all times?
待ち合わせ？
しかし 猿など今更…
はっ！　ああ そうか
なるほどのう
Oh, I see. So that's it. I guess my master put some thought into it.
我が主様にしては
考えたようじゃな
It was more the lineage's consciousness than the aberration.
怪異よりも あの小娘の場合は
血統の意識があった
Lineage's consciousness?
血統の意識？
You gave me some good information.
（忍）
いや よい情報を教えてくれた
これでムダ足にならずに済んだ
褒めて遣わすぞ
It kept my trip from being meaningless. I give you praise.
I was thinking I'd relax a bit by sucking your blood, but as thanks, I'll refrain.
気晴らしに うぬの血を
吸ってやろうかと思っておったが
礼として それは
やめておくことにする
Pretty close call.
Animation Number 344
What an absurd thing to think!
Pretty close call.
Animation Number 344
（ブラック羽川）
とんでもねえこと
思ってやがったにゃ
Pretty close call.
Animation Number 344
Or would you rather me suck your blood in thanks?
（忍）それとも 礼として
血を吸ってやったほうが
よいのじゃったかな？
I'll decline. The circumstances are slightly different nyow.
（ブラック羽川）
ハッ まあ 遠慮しておくにゃ
今回は ちょっと事情が違うにゃ
I feel there's a respectable mission waiting for me, meow.
今回の俺には
きっと れっきとした
使命があるはずにゃのにゃ
Though I don't know what exactly in purrticular.
それが何にゃのか
分からにゃいけれど
Understood
Animation Number 347
（忍）ふむ なるほどな
I see. Since you're like a new breed of aberration, I guess I shouldn't be too hasty in my decisions.
うぬは
新種の怪異のようなものじゃから
その辺は 軽々に
判断すべきではないか
I guess the difference between you now and before
言うなれば 前回までのうぬと
今回のうぬは
is like the difference between Terminator and Terminator 2.
「ターミネーター」と
「ターミネーター２」みたいな
ものなのじゃな
That was easy to understand, but is that how a vampire should repurresent it?
（ブラック羽川）
その例えは 理解しやすいが
しかし 吸血鬼のお前が
使っていいものにゃのか？
In any case, my sucking your blood is a very makeshift therapy.
まあ どっちにしても
わしが うぬの血を吸うというのは
こそく療法というか
所詮は その場しのぎにしか
すぎんからのう
It's only a temporary fix.
It shouldn't be something we use repeatedly.
あまり 何度も繰り返して
使うべき手法ではなかろう
Right. And I'm out in the open nyow like it's the way it's meant to be,
そうにゃ
それに こうやって
当たり前みたいに
堂々と表に出てきちゃあいるが
but I'm only my myaster's hidden
personality. I can't look dignified and stuff.
俺は あくまでも
ご主人の裏人格にゃ
堂々とにゃどしていたら
いけにゃいのにゃ
Open or hidden... it's merely two sides of the same coin.
（忍）表とか裏とか
そんなもんは 表裏一体みたいな
もんなのじゃがのう
My master's like this too, but you
unnecessarily spin aimlessly at times.
我が主様も大概じゃが
どうも うぬもうぬで
いらんところで空回りというか
空転しておる印象があるの
I get the impression you're getting nowhere.
Stay quiet and listen to a memoir from someone who's lived 500 years.
これは 500年生きた
わしの含蓄ある思い出話として
黙って聞け
This is a story about the emperor Napoleon. They say he only slept three hours each night.
ナポレオン皇帝の逸話なのじゃが
ヤツは１日に たった３時間しか
眠らなかったそうじゃな
Something wrong with that?
（ブラック羽川）
それがどうしたにゃん？
Just listen.
まあ 聞け
On the other hand, he was famous for loving baths.
一方で かの皇帝は
風呂好きで有名でな
They say he was in the bath more than six hours each day.
１日に６時間以上
風呂に入っておったという話じゃ
Yellow Scene
Animation Number 'none'
You could say a modern-day version would be Shizuka-chan.
今の時代で言えば
しずかちゃんじゃな
ふむ
Her knowledge is focused on the wrong things.
Animation Number 358
And after hearing both of these stories, I thought...
でな わしは
この２つの話を知ったとき
思ったんじゃよ
"No way! He had to have been sleeping in the bath!"
いやいや それ絶対
風呂の中で寝てたじゃろ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Oh, I see!
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（ブラック羽川）ああ にゃるほど
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
So I want to say even if two things seem
different, they might be linked in the end.
（忍）
つまるところ 別々の事柄のように
思えることでも
案外つながっておるのかもしれんと
わしは言いたいわけじゃ
There's no sense separating front from back when thinking.
表と裏を分離して考えることなど
意味はない
You may be Black Hanekawa, a severed portion of Hanekawa Tsubasa's persona,
うぬは 確かに 羽川翼から
人格的に切り離された—
ブラック羽川なのかもしれんが
but I sense that there isn't a definitive difference between you two.
しかし その両者に
確たる違いなどない
…と わしは思う
In my view, both aberrations and humans are rather similar.
わしから見れば 怪異も人間も
どっちも似たようなもんじゃしな
（ブラック羽川）そうか
I see.
My myaster and I are the same.
Now that you mention it...
Animation Number 370
（ブラック羽川）
俺と ご主人が同(おにゃ)じか
Sometimes I feel light as a feather,
and sometimes things weigh me down.
Animation Number 370
But then that's all the more reason that I can't have you suck my blood.
しかし だとすれば
ますます お前に
血を吸われるわけには
いかんということに
にゃるにゃ
It would be. Naturally disappearing would be best.
（忍）そうなるのう
自然消滅が
実は いちばんいいのじゃ
From a specialist and aberration's viewpoint.
専門家的にも もちろん
怪異的にもの
So, vampire, if you want to thank me, can you answer one of my questions?
（ブラック羽川）だから 吸血鬼
礼というにゃら 俺の質問に
ひとつ答えてくれにゃいか？
Well, I don't mind. But be quick about it. I must hurry over to where my master is.
（忍）
うん？　まあ 構わぬが
手早く頼むぞ
わしは 早く 我が主様のもとに
向かわねばならぬ
If I don't hurry, that good-for-nothing will die for sure this time.
早くせんと あの甲斐性(かいしょう)なしは
今度こそ殺されてしまう
Do you know a tiger aberration?
（ブラック羽川）
虎の怪異を知ってるか？
Tiger?
（忍）虎？
Yeah, a tiger. It's been myeandering about the city lately.
（ブラック羽川）ああ 虎にゃ
今 この町を
うろついているのにゃん
There are many tiger aberrations. Quite a few that even I know of.
（忍）
虎の怪異など いくらでもおるぞ
わしが知っておるだけでも
相当数じゃし
Combined with that Hawaiian-shirt guy's knowledge, it'd be at least fifty.
まして あのアロハ小僧の知識も
合わせるとなれば
優に50は超える
It's a myassive tiger.
（ブラック羽川）デッカい虎にゃ
Tigers usually are. Smaller would be better.
（忍野）虎は 大概デカい
小さい虎というのなら まだしも
Um, it's unimaginyably quick. It beat me to the punch like nothing.
（ブラック羽川）
う〜ん　すげえ速いにゃ
あっちゅう間に先回りされたにゃ
Tigers are usually agile. Motionless would be better.
（忍）虎は 大概 速い
動かぬ虎というものなら まだしも
Um, and it talks.
（ブラック羽川）
うう… あと しゃべるにゃ
Talks? An aberration that takes animal form yet speaks...
（忍）しゃべる？
動物型なのに しゃべる怪異か
That's, how do you say, rare.
それは なんというか 珍しいのう
But hearing that, I think I'm even more confused as to what it is.
しかし それを聞くと
より正体が 分からなく
なってしまった感があるぞ
Besides, if such an unknown aberration was walking around, there's no way I wouldn't notice.
大体 そんな正体不明の怪異が
町をうろついておれば
わしが気付かぬはずが
ないのじゃが
Are you saying you saw it?
うぬが その虎を
見たということなのか？
That's right, meow.
そうにゃ　いや 違う
No, that's not it. I did, but my myaster saw it before me. That's why I saw it, too.
俺も見たが それ以前に
俺のご主人が見たんにゃ
だから 俺も見た
That means that might be your focal point. In other words, an aberration only you can see.
（忍）
とすると その辺が
焦点なのかもしれんぞ
つまり
Aberration
Animation Number 386
うぬたちにしか
見えん怪異
Tiger
Animation Number 386
A tiger that only you can see.
うぬたちにしか見えん虎
It's a possibility. Sorry I couldn't help. I'll think about repaying you later.
可能性じゃがの
力になれなくて すまんな
礼は また考えておく
Hey, vampire.
（ブラック羽川）おい 吸血鬼
What is it, cat?
（忍）何じゃ？　猫
I'll give you a lift. It's one leap for me to get to those ruins.
（ブラック羽川）
送っていってやるにゃ
俺にゃら あの廃虚まで
ひとっ飛びにゃん
Animation Number 393
Don't be so alarmed. You can't fly right nyow, can you?
警戒するにゃよ
今のお前じゃ
空は飛べにゃいだろう？
It's not a purroblem for me. And you could save at least thirty minutes.
俺にとっては
大した手間じゃにゃい
でも 30分は短縮できるぞ
（忍）ふん
Yellow Scene
Animation Number 'none'
May I impose?
頼んでよいか？
Swift decision
Animation Number 395
Nyaturally.
もちろん　頼んでいいにゃん
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I carry her in my arms.
Animation Number 399
However.
Animation Number 409
However, we could never arrive.
Animation Number 410
All that was there was ashes. The place Araragi Koyomi and Oshino Shinobu used as a hideout.
（ブラック羽川）
あったのは 燃えカスだった
かつて 阿良々木暦と
忍野忍が隠れ家とし
Off
Limits
The place Oshino Meme lived for several months. The ruins of a cram school...
忍野メメが
数か月にわたって生活し
memorable to my myaster, Senjougahara Hitagi, Kanbaru Suruga, and Sengoku Nadeko.
ご主人や戦場ヶ原ひたぎ
神原駿河(するが)や千石撫子(せんごくにゃでこ)にとっても
思い出深い 学習塾跡の廃虚は…
That building that should have been there,
the abandoned ruin of that school, was not there.
Animation Number 413
Fire pump control panel
Fire extinguisher
foam tank
2000 liters
Fire extinguisher
foam tank
2000 liters
It was all burned to the ground.
全焼していたのにゃん
Preview
Dialogue Script - Nisio Isin
4-Koma Illustrations - Haritama Hiroki
Preview
Karen here!
（火憐）火憐だぜ！
（月火）月火だよ！
And Tsukihi!
I'm Tsukihi!
Together, we're the Fire Sisters!
We're the Fire Sisters!!
White Cat
（月火･火憐）
２人合わせて
“ファイヤーシスターズ”！
Nekomonogatari Shiro is going so fast we're already announcing the fourth episode!
Let's Be Friends!
Handshake?
Sounds Good!
（火憐）
早いもので「猫物語（白）」も
次で４匹目だぜ
（月火）
匹で数えるんだ？
So an episode is like a pet to you?
Preview Quick!
（火憐）予告編クイック
（月火）クイック？
Quick!?
Speaking of being quick, as I was playing with our brother I realized, aren't nail clippers awesome?
（火憐）
手早くいこうという意味だぜ
こないだ 兄ちゃんと遊んでいて
気付いたんだけど
爪切りって すごくね？
何これ？　誰が考えたの？
ENERGY
Who on earth thought them up?
They exist only for the purpose of clipping nails, but they're so simple even children can use them!
爪を切るためだけに存在する—
子供にでも簡単に使える
この刃物
これがなかったら
どれくらい不自由かって思わねえ？
Can you imagine how inconvenient a world without them would be?
（月火）
まあ 確かに不自由かも
ネイルケアできないかも
You're right. Maybe nail care wouldn't even exist!
DRAIN
And I'm not even finished. You can buy them real cheap in department stores,
（火憐）
刃物部分だけでも すげえのに
レバーと やすりを一体化させたり
you can carry them in a case so that your nails won't ever grow too long,
爪が飛び散らないよう
ケースを装着したり
is there no end to their value? Viva the Clipper!
その進化たるや
とどまるところを知らねえ
ビバ 爪切り！
Viva the Closure?
Fire Sisters Explision!
Ahh!
Bang
（月火）
ビバ 爪切り？
The "Awesome Spotlight Praise of the Nail Clippers" Quiz!
（火憐）
爪に火をともして作ったトーチで
褒めたたえてえぜ
That's it, I think I perfectly nailed their awesomeness!
以上 爪切りのすごさに関する
せつめいでした！
Did you have to end with such a lame pun?
（月火）
整えたあとに
なぜ余計なひと言を？
Next Time! Nekomonogatari Shiro Episode 4!
Next Time
Tsubasa Tiger Part 4
（火憐･月火）
次回「猫物語（白）」
第４話「つばさタイガー其ノ肆(そのよん)」
Tsubasa Tiger, Part 4.
By the way, how in the world did the two of you have fun with nail clippers?
She has grown an antenna!
Fired Up!
（月火）
ところで お兄ちゃんと
爪切りで どうやって遊んだの？
Well, my feet were...
（火憐）
え〜っと 足を…